What are the examples of CERATION?
So children, in the previous video you have learnt
what is the order of objects?
Based on the characteristics of the objects,
how they are arranged in large to small
or small to large order.
And this process of arranging things
in order is called SERIATION.
In this video we will see some examples
of SERIATION in which we will arrange different
people and objects in order based on their characteristics.
Today Chotu's class is going for a picnic.
And Chotu's teacher asks all the children
to stand in groups of four.
Then she asks the four children to stand
in a line in the small to large order
based on their height.
Chotu and his three other friends, Arthi, Neha and Sonu
begin to stand in a line.
First of all, being the shortest among all the four children,
Chotu stands in front.
Neha, who is taller than him
but shorter than the rest, stands behind him.
Sonu stands behind Neha.
Then finally, Arthi stands behind Sonu.
But Sonu just notices that he is taller than Neha
but falls to notice that Arthi is
shorter than him.
So children are Chotu and his friends
standing in the correct order of height.
Chotu and Neha are standing in the right order
but Sonu and Arthi are not.
Arthi realizes this as she is not able to
see anything by standing behind Sonu.
Therefore, Arthi should have stood in front of Sonu
as she is shorter than Sonu in height
but makes Sonu realize his mistake.
Sonu, just now you saw that you are taller
than Neha but you did not see that
I am also shorter than you.
I am taller than Neha and shorter than you.
So I should stand behind Neha
whereas I should stand in front of you.
Oh yes Arthi, you are absolutely right.
So children while making the order
Sonu saw that he was taller than the children standing
in front but he did not see
whether the children who were not standing in the line
are shorter in height than Sonu and hence
he made this mistake.
Finally, Chotu and three of his friends
stood in the correct increasing order
of their height that is from short to tall.
Children raised the bar for picnic.
There Chotu and his friends decide to play seven stones.
First of all, Arthi and Chotu start making a pile of stones
based on their size from big to small.
For this, Arthi gathers four stones from the surrounding.
Then she puts the biggest stone at the bottom.
To keep the rest of the stones,
she asks for Chotu's help.
Chotu now out of the remaining three stones
put the largest stone on this stone.
But Arthi, why are we placing these stones
in the big to small order?
If he plays a large size stone
on a small size stone, then it will fall down
because its balance will be disturbed.
Look Chotu just like this.
Therefore, we will place a big stone at the bottom
and then smaller than that so that
the balance of the stones is maintained.
Oh, okay.
Now out of the remaining two stones
put the big stone on top of these two stones.
Alright Arthi.
And now let's also put the large stone.
Very good Chotu.
Now our stone pile is ready.
Come on.
Let's place seven stones now.
Children, in this example you saw how Chotu
and Arthi made a pile of stones by keeping them
in the decreasing order of their size
one by one that is from large to small size.
So children tell me, did you enjoy seeing examples of seriation?
Okay, so that's all for today.
In this video we have learned
how to organize different people or objects
in order from small to large or from large to small.
I hope you have understood this topic properly.
Bye friends.